<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Duke Hamilton Earl of Cambridge his case, spoken to, and argued on the behalf of the Commonwealth, before the High Court of Justice. By Mr. Steel of Grays-Inn.</title>
            <author>Steele, William, d. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E558_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203635</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863521</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863521</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93849)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E558[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Duke Hamilton Earl of Cambridge his case, spoken to, and argued on the behalf of the Commonwealth, before the High Court of Justice. By Mr. Steel of Grays-Inn.</title>
                  <author>Steele, William, d. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Tyton, at the Three Daggers near the Inner Temple-Gate, Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Mr. Steel = William Steele.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "4th June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hamilton, James Hamilton, --  Duke of, 1606-1649.</term>
               <term>Trials (Treason) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115725:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Duke Hamilton Earl of <hi>CAMBRIDGE</hi> HIS CASE, Spoken to, and argued on the behalf OF THE Commonwealth, Before the HIGH COURT OF JUSTICE.</p>
            <p>By Mr. STEEL of <hi>Grays-Inn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Tyton,</hi> at the Three Daggers near the Inner <hi>Temple</hi>-Gate, Fleetſtreet, 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:115725:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115725:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Steel</hi>'s Speech before the High Court of JUSTICE, upon occaſion of the firſt coming of the Earl of <hi>Cambridge</hi> to the Bar, <hi>February</hi> 9. 1648.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat power which was at firſt in Families, Towns, and then in greater Collective bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, was after, for the better conſervation of the whole, dispoſed into bodies Politique and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative: <hi>Principium Originis</hi> is the priviledge of th'one, as <hi>Diſpenſationis</hi> of th'other; which distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as eaſily prevents all disputes about the preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of theſe powers, as it uſually ſatisfies that questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on touching bodies Natural, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the <hi>Primum ſenſorium</hi> be to be aſcribed to the heart or head? Of the birth and growth of theſe powers, God himſelf gave us ſome reſemblance, when that <hi>Lux primogenia,</hi> the light created on the first, was upon the fourth day contracted into thoſe heavenly lights, which were the first created Rulers of this world: The powers of men thus ſetled, were inveſted with various immunities, ſuitable to their Offices, as ſo many beams flowing from them for the good of mankinde; and amongſt theſe, I know none more bright and influential to the world, then that of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> which when 'tis rightly darted into
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115725:3"/>the hearts and hands of men, doth not prove like that ſword behinde the <hi>Ephod,</hi> but rather as that of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon,</hi> and ſometimes upon juſt occaſion, like that which hung over the head of <hi>Damocles,</hi> ready to do ſpeedy and impartial execution: Of this power I both ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this Honorable Court to be the proper Subject, and the now Priſoner at Bar the proper Object.</p>
            <p>The proceedings of <hi>Juſtice</hi> are call'd, Streams of Righteouſneſs for their clear and current paſſage: And (my Lord, what if no gallant Ship nor Galley with oars, ſail in theſe of yours? yet if the glorious Lord vouchſafe you his preſence he will be broad Rivers to you; what if others of inferior rank, ſpare not to load your perſons and actions with reproaches? yet you know, not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Latratus Canum,</hi> what's the poſture of that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful witneſs in heaven, <hi>Et peragit curſus ſurda Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ſuos:</hi> And as for this Lord, brought by a divine hand to appear thus before you, I may ſay of him, <hi>Quae alios diviſa reos faciunt in hunc conjuncta flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt,</hi> ſo fit is he to ſtand at the Bar of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> to look upon him as he now appears, may perhaps move compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as once <hi>Date obolum Belliſario</hi> did to that great Commander (and indeed (my Lord) however his Crime may be above your mercy, yet I would not have his better part either be beyond your prayers or pity) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthêleſs, that you may take a right view of thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for which he is here convented, I wiſh he may rather
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115725:3"/>be look'd upon as marching the last Summer in the head of twenty thouſand men, in an Hostile and Treacherous maner to invade this Nation, as if that which ſome feared in the Argument of <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe, if the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould paſs, as it after wards did, were under this mans conduct come to paſs; <hi>viz.</hi> That the the Scots, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of ſuch a priviledge as to be Denizens of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> would thereafter come like <hi>avers ſans number</hi> into the Engliſh Commons; or as if he were willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the truth of that obſervation of <hi>Comities,</hi> that what <hi>Portugal</hi> was to <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Venetians</hi> and <hi>Florentines</hi> then to <hi>Italy,</hi> that was <hi>Scotland</hi> of old to <hi>England,</hi> a ſcourge to minde them of their duties to God, and to keep them humble: But more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to touch the aggravating circumſtances of this horrid Treaſon, and therein to omit the mentioning of thoſe perſonal benefits this Nation had afforded him, by making him capable of their own Dignities, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, equal to any Natural born Engliſhman, and to take the dimenſions more peculiar to this Rebellion: We were the laſt year after a tedious ſtorm of War, beginning to rejoyce in the hopes of ſeeing the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of this State, come ſafe into the harbor of Peace, but the enemies of <hi>Englands</hi> happineſs, and of their own, were not willing to enjoy this bleſsing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Terms it was purchaſed; an harmonious ſpirit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115725:4"/>muſt paſs betwixt the South and North, the veſſel again lanch into the deep, all our hopes of ſettlement be indangered, and the poor waſted Northern counties, which ere now expected a <hi>Jubile,</hi> muſt by theſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in cruelty be uſed like <hi>Sechemites,</hi> and again tormented, before they be healed of their old ſores; as if they now came to take <hi>Livery</hi> and <hi>Seiſin</hi> of thoſe counties, which ſome affirm were promiſed them as part of their reward for this ſervice: And all this, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe ſolemn Treaties tranſacted in <hi>1642.</hi> and <hi>1643.</hi> for the Vnion of both Kingdoms, and thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements not to make War each with other, before three moneths warning, nor to Gariſon <hi>Berwick</hi> or <hi>Carliſle,</hi> without conſent of both Parliaments; ſo alſo against the frequent premonitions of the General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in <hi>Scotland</hi> (the Aſſembly here alſo by their Letter, ſignifying their concurrence with thoſe endeavors of the Scotiſh Divines) and both agreeing, this Expedition to be againſt, not for the ends of the <hi>Covenant;</hi> but whilest theſe Invaders were thus forewan'd, they not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding forearm themſelves in the worſt ſence for us: But two circumſtances above all ſeem to me, to extend the vileneſs of this fact beyond all aggravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the one, That the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> whilest they in <hi>Scotland</hi> were forming their weapons againſt us, by their Commiſsioners reſiding there, often
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115725:4"/>ſignified their deſires of preſereving a Brotherly Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; howbeit, inſtead of receiving any other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, we muſt be anſwered, <hi>Per argumenta ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culina:</hi> the other, That their coming in muſt be for the ends of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> that being uſually made the stock whereon to graſt their desperate Deſigns; thinking thereby, as to mask their own deformities, ſo to ſeduce many well meaning men into their conſederacy; and from thence as this third War was called <hi>Bellum Hypocritarum,</hi> ſo may the Priſoner, under whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in chief they came, be justly stiled <hi>Hypocrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Princeps:</hi> The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon appealed to heaven by their Declaration, and therein Prophetically spake what came to paſs, That they doubted not but God would be with them, and the prayers of his people for them; and that thoſe who had dealt falſly, in ſtriking hands with the common Enemy, to kindle a new fire betwixt theſe kingdoms, ſhould periſh themſelves therein; upon which appeal the higheſt <hi>Judge</hi> gave out his righteous decree, <hi>&amp; ſpes hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum periit;</hi> and had he not indeed appeared for his despiſed people, by a more then ordinary rule of his diſpenſation, and inabled a ſmall company of men, like ſtars in their courſe, to fight against and vanquiſh this <hi>Siſera</hi> and his mighty Host, <hi>England</hi> doubtleſs ere this had been a Field of Blood: Of this unnatural and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115725:5"/>unchristian Army thus totally by a power from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven routed, <hi>habemus ducem,</hi> we have here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the principal Author and Actor, againſt whom the pillaged depopulated counties, the blood of many inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, many of his own Countreymen both at home, and now in forreign parts, and God himſelf, by the strange and ſpeedy delivery of him into your hands, after his eſcape from <hi>Windſor,</hi> coming himſelf ſooner then poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he could have done if ſent for, immediately after the former execution, do all unanimouſly call for a just ſentence, and the ſame do I in the Name of the People of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="charge_and_plea">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115725:5"/>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Charge being read againſt the ſaid Earl, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter of High Treaſon, for his invatling this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in an Hoſtile maner, and levying actual War there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, he thereunto put in this enſuing Plea.</p>
               </argument>
               <head>The Plea of <hi>Iames</hi> Earl of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> whereby (as he alleaged) he was not to be tryed for Treaſon within this Kingdom.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>THat he was imployed by the Parliament of the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, <hi>not to invade this Kingdom, but for the ends they have declared, ſent to the Parliament of the Kingdom of</hi> England.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>That he is no Engliſhman, notwithſtanding the Naturalization of his Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That he is a Priſoner of War, rendred upon Articles by Major General</hi> Lambert; <hi>and that thoſe Capitulations were made before his Rendition with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor General</hi> Lamberts <hi>Commiſsioners.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115725:6"/>
            <head>THE ARGUMENT of Mr. <hi>Steel,</hi> On the behalf of the COMMON-VVEALTH, Touching the matter of Law in the CASE of the Earl of <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Councel for the Earl of <hi>Cambridge</hi> have framed their Arguments upon the fact, as they conceive it proved; and alſo by admittance of the contrary in ſome points, I ſhall uſe the ſame method, firſt, Arguing from the fact, as I conceive it ſtated by the proofs produced, and then by admittance of the contrary, that though the fact ſhould be as they would have it, that yet the Law will fall out to be againſt them.</p>
            <p>The Charge being read to the Priſoner, he hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto put in his Plea, conſiſting of three parts; the truth and validity whereof hath been denyed on the behalf of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The firſt part of his Plea was, That he was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the Parliament of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> not to invade this Kingdom, but for the ends declared by them: The improvement made of this part of the Plea, is, That the Earl was but a Servant in this Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and under the Authority and command of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and tyed under Oathes and penalties to give obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; if he had diſobeyed, he had been liable to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115725:6"/>therefore it were hard for him to be puniſhed for obeying alſo: That he hath not exceeded his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; beſides the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in their Declaration of the 17 of <hi>February</hi> laſt, lay the blame of this Invaſion upon the Parliament of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And laſtly, That the Earls caſe is not unlike that of an Ambaſſador, who is not to be blamed for acting againſt a State, if he have it in <hi>mandatis,</hi> as in the caſe of the Biſhop of <hi>Roſs,</hi> in the Reign of Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By endeavor to give ſatisfaction to all which, I ſhall diſpatch what I have to ſay upon this firſt part of the Plea.</p>
            <p>I ſhall admit it proved, that he had that Commiſſion and Authority mentioned; and alſo, that the rule is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally true, That a man is not to be puniſhed for an act which he doth by the neceſſity of obedience, becauſe he hath nor <hi>ſolutum arbitrium,</hi> which is required to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominate actions either blame-worthy or excuſable; but I ſhall eaſily prove, that this Rule is capable of reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; both by the Rules of Law and Reaſon, and if we obſerve the diſtinctions aright which determine this queſtion, we ſhall ſtill finde the Earl of <hi>Cambridge</hi> within that part which renders him inexcuſable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The firſt difference is, where the Action is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and where unlawful which is commanded: If it be lawful, a Superior command may diſpence with ſome circumſtances; but if unlawful, the Servant obeying, is not the leſs to be blamed: I never held that Law of <hi>Ina</hi> the <hi>Saxon</hi> King to be warrantable Divinity, <hi>Servus ſi quid operis patrarit die Dominico ex precepto Domini ſui Eiber eſto,</hi> if the precept it ſelf were unjuſt.</p>
            <p>Now for the Action in queſtion, wherein this Earl was engaged, it is not defended by his own Councel, the diſpute being onely <hi>de modo,</hi> whether he be to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115725:7"/>as an Enemy, or as Traytor, though if this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument held, he were neither way to be puniſhed, and therefore certainly the neceſſity of his obedience is no mitigation for his Crime; and if it ſhould, <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley,</hi> with all their Monopolizing Succeſſors, had been unjuſtly cenſured, who always have had Patents and Commiſſions from Authority to plead: And ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all that catalogue of former Traytors, who have hatched their Treaſons and Deſigns againſt this State in Forreign parts, and have ever had the Pope or Forreign Princes to put a ſtamp of Authority and command up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, muſt by this Argument be in ſome meaſure juſtified.</p>
            <p>It was never expected from any under command, to write himſelf more a ſervant then <hi>uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad aras,</hi> thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Hercules</hi>'s pillars whereon a <hi>non plus ultra</hi> is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and therefore who ever exceeds thoſe bounds, he will finde it to be at his peril.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſecond difference is, where the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is <hi>inanimatum,</hi> and where an Active living inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; of the firſt it is truly ſaid, <hi>Inſtrumenti nulla vis,</hi> all being therein attributed to the principal efficient, but otherwiſe of the other: From hence the Statute of 1, 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Ma. ca.</hi> 10. did juſtly repeal the Statute of 33 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 20. which had puniſhed a man for Treaſon, though he became <hi>non compos mentis</hi> before the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and no leſs juſtly did 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>de proditionibus</hi> by the word <hi>(Imagination)</hi> alter in the like point that Law which was in uſe till then, concerning ſuch a perſons com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the act of Treaſon, ſuch an one being no better then <hi>quaſi inanimatus:</hi> But who can affirm this Earl to be other then an active and vigorous inſtrument, <hi>non modo vivit ſed in ſenatum venit,</hi> being a chief Member of that Parliament, under whoſe command he would ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115725:7"/>himſelf, and by that means is a Maſter rather then a Servant, and ſo met with by that Declaration of the Parliament of this Kingdom, of which he would have made an Argument for himſelf.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Where there is <hi>neceſsitas culpabilis,</hi> the Law will not excuſe, as it will where there is no crime in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting the neceſſity: Thoſe who in former times gave victuals and proviſion to Sir <hi>John Oldcaſtle,</hi> were not puniſhed as Traytors, becauſe they did it (ſay our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords) <hi>Pro timore Mortis, &amp; receſſerunt quam citò po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuerunt,</hi> 3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 10. and upon this reaſon ſeems that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Tremayle</hi> to be grounded in 21 <hi>H.</hi> 7.39. That a Servant may juſtifie the killing of another, to ſave his Maſters life, if he cannot otherwiſe eſcape.</p>
            <p>But if one being drunk commits a crime, though he hath not properly and immediately the free exerciſe of his will, yet the Law reputes him <hi>voluntarius Daemon,</hi> and he is not at all the leſs excuſable by our Law, 1 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 247. 4 <hi>li. Beverleys</hi> Caſe; and by the Philoſophers Rule, ſuch a one doth <hi>ignorans,</hi> not <hi>per ignorantiam agere,</hi> and is therein ſo far from being excuſed, that he is therefore to be doubly puniſhed.</p>
            <p>Now to aſſume, that whereby the Earls Councel would excuſe him; <hi>viz.</hi> His Oath and Commiſſion, renders him the leſs excuſable, becauſe both are ſtrong Arguments of a free and full conſent; for who can imagine them of <hi>Scotland</hi> to be ſuch mean Statiſts, as to think that Oath equally obliging, which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſive, to the ſame, if freely taken; or that that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſhould be truſted with a Commiſſion over all their Forces both by Sea and Land, as his Commiſſion runs, whoſe heart as well as hand had not imbraced it; and truly, they that have heard his Letters read to Sir <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduke Langdale,</hi> wherein he prays for the increaſe of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115725:8"/>the diſtractions at <hi>London,</hi> and for his friends at <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> would not judge him an unwilling inſtrument, but one exceeding, rather then falling ſhort in executing his Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Neceſsity of obedience may excuſe in <hi>privatis,</hi> but never in <hi>publicis:</hi> If a Feme covert together with her husband, commit an act which in another would amount to felony, yet in her it ſhall not, becauſe <hi>ſub poteſtate viri,</hi> 27 <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 40. but otherwiſe the Law is in point of Treaſon, &amp; ſo is the judgement of my Lord <hi>Verulam, Nes valet privilegium</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>contra rem-publicam.</hi> And as to the caſe of an Ambaſſador urged on the other ſide, and in particular of the Biſhop of <hi>Roſs</hi> in the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> I anſwer, firſt, The priviledges of thoſe who are entertained as Ambaſſadors, are very great, and not to be made preſidents or aſſum'd by any other, whence <hi>Proregis Dedecus redundat in regem,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. it was Treaſon to kil an Ambaſſador, 22 <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 48. and from hence might ariſe that priviledge ſhewed to the Biſhop of <hi>Roſs.</hi> Secondly, It appears to be rather an Act of Grace then of Juſtice, that, that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop was freed, becauſe he was ſet at liberty after a long impriſonment, which if not lyable to the cenſure of the Law, he ſhould not at all in Juſtice have endured: Alſo by the judgement of my Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> cited by the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctor on the other ſide, in point of conſpiracy againſt the State, even an Ambaſſador is not priviledged; yet of this Biſhop learned <hi>Cambden</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Eliz. Fuit libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus que rebellioni clam faces ſubjecerat,</hi> all which were Arguments of Grace, and therefore that caſe will be no preſident for this, wherein alſo conſpiracies and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencies, with many of this Nation have been proved, and are otherwiſe notorious.</p>
            <p>And for that inevitable labyrinth out of which the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115725:8"/>Earl of <hi>Cambridge</hi> cannot extricate himſelf, but that whether obey or not obey, he is under a miſchief, he may for that thank himſelf, <hi>volenti non fit injuria,</hi> this is like the plague of an Erroneous Conſcience, which whether obeyed or not, proves a tormentor to its ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſecond part of the Earls Plea is, That he is no Engliſhman, notwithſtanding the Naturaliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Father; which in effect is as much as to ſay, and ſo it hath been inſiſted on, He is by birth a Scots man, and by conſequence an Alien to, and not tryable as a Traytor by, the Laws of <hi>England:</hi> Concerning the handling of which queſtion, it being that whereupon the validity of the other two doth in my judgement principally depend, I ſhall firſt anſwer the material Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections which I conceive, made by the Councel on the other ſide, before I offer any thing poſitively to aſſert the invalidity of this part of the Plea.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>It hath been ſaid, The proof is not clear, for the Earl of</hi> Cambridge <hi>his being a</hi> Poſtnatus; viz. <hi>One born after King</hi> James his <hi>Acceſs to the Crown of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>and that being but a</hi> non liquet, in favorem vitae, <hi>the moſt favorable conſtruction is to be taken for the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny that the proof amounts to no more in this particular then a <hi>non liquet,</hi> for there is one poſitive witneſs that ſpeaks directly to the Earls birth, after King <hi>James</hi> his coming to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> another ſpeaks to the Earls own confeſſion, of being about two or three and forty years of age, which ſpeaks him born ſince that time; and a third ſpeaks to the common report of his being born ſince; and if the proof were but <hi>ſemiplena probatia;</hi> yet as <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, That amounts to a preſumption; and, ſaith he, <hi>Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptioni
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115725:9"/>ſtabitur donec probetur in contrerium,</hi> eſpecially when the Earl himſelf, who ſhould have proved the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary for the making good his Plea, hath offered nothing againſt it, and being asked, never abſolutely deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I do agree, that what the Jewiſh Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors obſerve in the Expoſition of their Laws, which ſounded in favor, is to be obſerved in our Law, in thoſe things which we uſually ſay the Law favors; <hi>viz. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vores ſunt ampliandi,</hi> and that ſtrict Expoſitions are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for penal Rules, according to that of the <hi>Civilians, Conſtitutio penalis non excedit caſum,</hi> yet we ſhall finde; that where the penalty of a penal Law is againſt one or few perſons, and the benefit redounds to the generality, in that caſe even a penal Statute ſhall be taken largely againſt the Offendor, ſo the Rule is put <hi>Plow. Com.</hi> 36. <hi>Plats</hi> Caſe, where it is reſolved, though the Statute of 1 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. give an Action of eſcape againſt the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the Fleet; yet for the reaſon aboveſaid, it is, though a penal Law, by a benign interpretation, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the Sheriff of <hi>London;</hi> and in like maner if there were any latitude in Caſes of Treaſon and Murther (as there is not) yet to extend it on the behalf of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, might prove to many thouſands, <hi>Crudelis miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recordia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Adde to this, that the Law of <hi>England</hi> is ſo tender of the Publique Weal, that though in other Caſes it may ſeem to inſiſt too much upon formalities, yet herein it will diſpence ſometimes with its moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rules: Hence it is, that if one paſs over anothers Land without his conſent, to fetch a Falcon, or the like, he may be puniſhed as a Treſpaſſer; but not ſo, if to hunt or kill a Fox or an Otter (which inſtances, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not unſuitable to the Priſoner) becauſe theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115725:9"/>are Creatures <hi>contra bonum Publicum,</hi> which reaſon the Book gives of the Law in that Caſe, 12 <hi>H.</hi> 8.10. for the ſame reaſon, no man ſhall be puniſhed as a Treſpaſſer for erecting Bulwarks on anothers Land, <hi>Dyer</hi> 36. <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verers</hi> Caſe: And hence certainly was the reaſon of that ancient Law, That Capital Offenders who had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed againſt the Law, had <hi>Lupina Capita,</hi> and might therefore by the Juſtice of <hi>Lex talionis, arteperire ſuâ;</hi> wherein the Law followed <hi>Naturae ordinem:</hi> The rules of nature are moſt conſtant, yet for the preſervation of the whole, it will ſometimes contradict it ſelf, as to prevent a <hi>vacuum</hi> and the like, what an inverſion do we ſee of natures moſt conſtant and ordinary Rules: Do not they then in this prove ſomewhat unnatural, and imbrace a cloud in ſtead of ſubſtance, that fear not to omit the weightieſt things of the Law, rather then in caſes of invincible neceſſity, diſpence with ſome formalities?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But though the Earl of</hi> Cambridge <hi>were a</hi> Poſtnatus, <hi>yet he is</hi> quaſi Ligeus acquiſitus <hi>unto</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and if ſo, as his Allegiance began with an Act of the Nation, ſo it might determine by an Act of the ſame Power, to wit, by Command from the Parliament of</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſtrength of this Objection, if admitted, would, as I conceive, by a new invented di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, overthrow the learned and ſolemn reſolution of all the Judges and Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> 6 <hi>Jac.</hi> in <hi>Calvins Caſe,</hi> wherein all Allegiances that the wits of men could imagine are enumerated, and they are but four; <hi>viz. Ligeantia Naturalis, Acquiſita, Localis,</hi> and <hi>Legalis;</hi> and by the Judgement of that Caſe, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Calvin,</hi> Son and Heir to <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Calvin</hi> of <hi>Colcroſs</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> born three years after King <hi>James</hi> his acceſs to the Crown (as alſo all other ſo born) were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115725:10"/>adjudged Subjects of this Kingdom of <hi>England Lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antiâ Naturali,</hi> by the beſt and higheſt Allegiance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>quaſi</hi> at all, in the ſame kinde, and to all intents and purpoſes that any natural born Engliſhman was.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Objection ſeems to me, not onely to be againſt the Judgement of this Caſe, but againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alſo; for what acquiſition is there by the party, or what contributes he to it, whether he be born in this or that time or place; the conceit, that there is any act of the party's in this (as there muſt be to make a <hi>quaſi Lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us acquiſitus</hi>) ſeems to ſavor of the <hi>Pythagorean Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempſucoſis,</hi> or that opinion of <hi>Plato,</hi> who held a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtence of Souls, which after came into the bodies, <hi>tanquam in ergaſtula.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>It is inconſiſtent to have two natural Allegiances to two ſeveral Kingdoms, as it is impoſsible to have two Fathers, in which Caſe</hi> major relatio trahet ad ſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem, <hi>and in that caſe the Earl is rather to be reputed a Subject of</hi> Scotland <hi>where he was born, then of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is indeed inconſiſtent that the ſame perſon ſhould in two ſeveral Kingdoms have two origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Allegiances, in a phyſical acceptation, to wit, to be ſo born; yet by conſtruction of Law, he that is born in <hi>Scotland,</hi> may have an Allegiance to <hi>England,</hi> equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent with the other; thus <hi>Calvin</hi> by the reſolution of that Caſe was <hi>Scotus patriâ,</hi> and <hi>Anglus privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus without any contradiction, it was ever held for Law, That the Natives of <hi>Gaſcoign</hi> and <hi>Aquitain,</hi> and thoſe other countreys which were Geographically out of <hi>England,</hi> were yet in conſtruction of Law, equally Denizens and Subjects of <hi>England</hi> with thoſe born here, in regard of one Allegiance and Protection
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115725:10"/>wherein they were equally involved, 27 <hi>Aſſ. Pl.</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>Secondly, No Allegiance which gains the name of <hi>alta &amp; Naturalis Ligeantia,</hi> can by the Common Law of <hi>England</hi> be deveſted, though otherwiſe it may be by the Civil Laws, there being no <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus</hi> that its capable of, which the Objection would ſuppoſe; and the truth is, The reſolution of <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe, anſwers all the ſuppoſitions of any future contingencies, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively reſolves, That this Allegiance cannot poſſibly be loſt by any matter <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> no, not by difference of diſcents and Governments, 7 <hi>Li.</hi> 27. and what is agreed to be inherent to a natural born Engliſhman, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs alſo to a <hi>Poſtnatus, non poteſt patriam in quo natus eſt exuere, nec Ligeantiae Debitum ejurare,</hi> 1 Inſt. 129.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, And for the inconſiſtences of Allegiancies that the objection ſeems to inſinuate, in the caſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition between the Kingdoms, <hi>Bracton</hi> hath met with that ſuppoſal long ſince, <hi>Li. de. exeptionibus</hi> 427. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one that is <hi>ad fidem utrinſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Regis, ſi contingat gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erram accidere inter Regna,</hi> putting the caſe of one born in <hi>France,</hi> and Indenized in <hi>England, Remaneat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonaliter cum eo cui Ligeantiam fecerit, &amp; faciat ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium debitum ei cum quo non ſteterit in perſonâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Though the Earl of</hi> Cambridge <hi>were a</hi> Poſtnatus, <hi>yet as this Caſe is, it makes him not to differ from an Alien, becauſe the Kingdoms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland <hi>were at the time of this Invaſion divided, and there were then ſeveral Adminiſtrations of their powers, from whence a double Allegiance is to be conſidered,</hi> Regis &amp; Regni.</p>
            <p>Firſt. <hi>Anſ.</hi> If we look upon the judicial powers of the Kingdoms in a Legal conſideration, even at the time mentioned in the Objection, beſides the Union of the Kingdoms made by force of 1 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1. we ſhall finde
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115725:11"/>as ſtrong Stipulations and Engagements by Treaties confirmed by Parliament and otherwiſe, betwixt the Nations, as were poſſibly to be made, none of which were repealed at the time of this expedition, and ſo far from that, that the Earl himſelf hath often at the Bar profeſt, That neither his coming nor Commiſſion were againſt the Parliament or Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> How then were the powers of theſe Nations ſo legally or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially different?</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Union of the Laws and Governments of theſe Nations, was a thing deſired and endeavored by ſome, as may appear by the latter part of the Statute of 4 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1. but it was not effected; therefore the diſtinction of the Kingdoms was taken into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe, where <hi>(Regna)</hi> was one of the <hi>Nomina operativa,</hi> and granted, That though the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Laws, and Nobilities of the Nations of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> were ſeveral and diſtinct, yet the Allegiance of all born in either Nation after the union, was one and the ſame; and the pleading of that caſe (which beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes the Law) demonſtrates this, That ſuch diſtinction of the Kingdoms was under conſideration; for the pleading was, That <hi>Calvin</hi> was born <hi>extra Ligeantiam Regni Regis Angliae,</hi> and <hi>infra Ligeantiam Regni Regis Scotia;</hi> and the learned Chancellor of that time ſaith in his <hi>Poſtnati,</hi> that the judgement was, That neither <hi>Calvin,</hi> nor any other <hi>Poſtnati,</hi> were Aliens to the King or Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is agreed on the other ſide, That there was always one <hi>Ligeantia Regis;</hi> and therefore even thence I do infer, that there was alſo one <hi>Ligeantia Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> becauſe that Allegiance which was due to the King, was certainly due to him in his politique capacity, though not to that onely, or divided in the Subject from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115725:11"/>his natural capacity; however it may be ſaid neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as it is in <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe (by a community of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties) that it was due to the natural capacity alſo, <hi>viz.</hi> As it ought ever to be accompanied with the politique, thence it was but juſt in the Parliament, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kings Perſonal Command and Oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, yet to permit the taking of the Oath of Allegiance, and not to aboliſh it till after his death, it being <hi>ad Legem Ligatio,</hi> yet the perſon was ſo neceſſary, that without it, it had been ridiculous to adminiſter it in the form it was, in which caſe <hi>majus dignum trabit ad ſe minus;</hi> and hence it was, that capital crimes committed in one Kings time, might be proceeded againſt after the death of that King 3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Fitz. Reattachment</hi> 18. &amp; <hi>Bro. Corone,</hi> 178. If the King had purchaſed Land to him and his Heirs, though the word <hi>(Succeſſors)</hi> the word of his politique capacity, had not been mentioned, yet he was feiſed thereof in <hi>jure Coronae,</hi> 43 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.20. And if Land had been given to the King and another, and their Heirs, they had for the ſame reaſon been Tenants in Common, and not Joynt-Tenants, <hi>Com.</hi> 239. for the ſame reaſon: And though many of thoſe perſons who have been Kings, have often oppreſſed, in ſtead of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved their Subjects; yet ſtill that which <hi>Bracton</hi> hath ſaid upon the ſame ground, remains true of the Regal Power, <hi>Non aliud Rex poteſt quam quod de jure poteſt,</hi> his Office ſtill being <hi>Ex Officio,</hi> as 2 <hi>Li. Coo. Wiſemans</hi> Caſe ſaith, and <hi>Fitz. na. bre.</hi> 113. out of the Regiſter, to provide for the preſervation of his People; and if any other conſtruction ſhould be made, then it muſt have followed in the Kings Perſonal abſence, minority, or diſability, the Kingdom muſt either have been but weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or not at all govern'd; from all which it may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd, That the Obligation and Allegiance which was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115725:12"/>owing to the King, did include, that which <hi>Savo ſenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was the Kingdoms alſo.</p>
            <p>It remains now, that ſomewhat be ſpoken for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther invalidating of this part of the Plea, wherein I ſhall</p>
            <p>Firſt prove, That one born in <hi>Scotland</hi> after the Union of the Crowns, cannot be to any purpoſe conſidered as an Alien to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That though the Earl of <hi>Cambridge</hi> had been born before the Union, yet he had not been an Alien to <hi>England;</hi> partly from a National conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but more principally from perſonal conſiderations; <hi>viz.</hi> firſt, By reaſon of his Local Allegiance both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Ligeantiâ acquiſitâ,</hi> and that by the Naturalization of his Father, or his own Denization.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That though he had been an Alien, yet as this caſe is upon the proofs, he will prove tryable for Treaſon by the Laws of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Before I ſpeak of any of theſe, I might touch upon that part which layeth Murther to the charge of this Earl; it having been fully proved, That ſeveral perſons by name, amongſt many others, were ſlain and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by the Scotiſh Army; and to make him puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for this Crime, there is no need of denization, it being an offence in it ſelf againſt the Law of God and Nations, and we truſt, requiſite to be an ingredient to it, as is required in Treaſon: Hence we finde Rape pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable in <hi>England,</hi> committed by a Scot, 13 <hi>Eliz. Dyer</hi> 304. and Murther done by the Lord <hi>Zanchar</hi> of the ſame Nation, 9 <hi>Li. Coo.</hi> 116. where we finde him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by the Name of <hi>Robert Creighton</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> which together with the expreſs Authority of 11 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>Fitz. bre.</hi> 473. are (by the way) ſufficient warrants for our charging the Priſoner by the Name of <hi>James</hi> Earl of <hi>Cambridge,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115725:12"/>without mentioning his Dukedom, as he hath often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated we ſhould have done.</p>
            <p>And if the Earl ſhould ſay, He kill'd not theſe perſons himſelf, his Councel can ſoon tell him, That's not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, the Law being, That if divers perſons come to do an unlawful act, and one commit a Murther or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, its ſo in all, 1 <hi>Mar. Dyer</hi> 38. 13 <hi>H.</hi> 4.13. 19 <hi>Ed.</hi> 2 <hi>Fitz. Cor.</hi> 433. But the truth is, I ſhall not rely upon this, being not willing ſo high an offence ſhould paſs under any other name then that of Treaſon; therefore I paſs to thoſe aforementioned conſiderations, which will evince his Crime to be no leſs then Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the firſt of theſe, there being ſo much ſaid in the Argument of <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe, I ſhall omit the citing of any thing particularly from thence, and ſelect ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the Statutes made ſhortly after the Union. Its agreed by all Hiſtorians, That theſe two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms were anciently but one, <hi>Diviſos orbe Britannos, &amp; ſabducta Britannia mundo;</hi> thence its obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, That in the Preface of 1 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 1. by the acceſs of the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> to this Kingdom; the Parliament ſpeaking of the Union, correct themſelves in theſe words, or rather a reuniting of theſe two Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (though anciently but one;) if ſo, this reunion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to no leſs then (as it were) a National remitter of the ancient Union.</p>
            <p>For the ſettlement of this Union, Commiſſioners were choſen to compoſe ſome differences betwixt the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to conſider what was fit and neceſſary to be done for the Commonweal of both Kingdoms, 1 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 2. Theſe Commiſſioners conſult long about it, and becauſe they could not perfect it within the time prefixt, an Act paſſeth for longer time, 3 <hi>Jac. cap.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>At length the work is finiſht by the Statute of 4 <hi>Jaco.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115725:13"/>cap.</hi> 1. by which all Statutes that expreſs or imply any ſtrangeneſs of the one Nation to the other are repealed; and moreover, it doth Enact and ſay, <hi>That if there had appeared any other Statutes of this Realm of</hi> England, <hi>wherein any thing is Ordained, Enacted and Eſtabliſhed expreſly, and by name, againſt the Scotiſh as Enemies, or Scotland as an</hi> Enemy Countrey <hi>to the King of this Realm, or the</hi> State <hi>of the ſame, we ſhould for ſo much of them as concerneth Scottiſh men or</hi> Scotland, <hi>have utterly abrogated and adnulled the ſame, ſeeing all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Hoſtility of former times between the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and People is now happily taken away.</hi> So the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute. After which it ſeems as ſtrange, that any born in <hi>Scotland,</hi> after, and during the continuance of that Union, ſhould make themſelves ſtrangers to <hi>England;</hi> as if natural born Engliſh men ſhould have made the ſame allegation.</p>
            <p>In the aforeſaid Statute of 4 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. there is a clauſe, That no Scotiſhman coming into <hi>England</hi> to proſecute the Law againſt any Engliſhman, offending in <hi>Scotland,</hi> is to be arreſted here, except for Treaſon and Murther; and in the latter end of the Act, amongſt other things, it is Enacted, <hi>That if any Engliſhman ſhould commit Treaſon or other Crimes in</hi> Scotland, <hi>and come into</hi> England, <hi>he ſhould not upon his apprehenſion here be ſent into Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to have his Tryal there, but be tryed where he is taken;</hi> but the Statute of 7 <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 1. which was the year after the reſolution in <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe, repealed that clauſe of 4 <hi>Jac.</hi> 1. laſt mentioned, as to all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences but Treaſon, leaving the offendors in that kinde to be tryed in the Kingdom where they were appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; and though the Statute ſpeak onely of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, yet the like Act was to paſs in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in caſe any of that Nation committed Treaſon here, elſe neither was to be binding to the Nations.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115725:13"/> 2. In the next place, ſomewhat may be ſaid from a National Conſideration to prove the Earl no alien here, though born before the Union, not that my purpoſe is to endeavor the revival of that ancient homage done formerly by that Kingdom to this, it is not worth the mentioning, in compariſon of that love and thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements which have been betwixt us, <hi>Gens una ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> was heretofore ſaid of us, and if it may be, I wiſh, <hi>Sic ſimus in aevum;</hi> but becauſe ſomewhat hath been on the other ſide cited from the ſtories of <hi>Bruce</hi> and <hi>Baliol,</hi> in the days of <hi>Edward</hi> 1. and for that I finde both Law and Hiſtory afford ſome matter for this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I hold it my duty not to be altogether ſilent in what paſſed in thoſe times and ſince: I will not inſiſt up-thoſe ſeveral Appeals made by <hi>Magdolphus</hi> and others of the Scotiſh Nation to <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>contra cuſtodes Scotiae,</hi> and againſt the Kings of <hi>Scotland</hi> themſelves, all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of allegiance then acknowledged from that Kingdom to this.</p>
            <p>But to inſtance in ſome Preſidents neerer to this in queſtion, <hi>Simon Fryſel,</hi> in 34 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>anno</hi> 1306. a Native of <hi>Scotland,</hi> came in an hoſtile manner from that Kingdom to invade this, and being apprehended here, he was condemned as a Traytor; the words of <hi>Math. Weſt,</hi> 456. concerning him, are, That he was <hi>a turri Londinenſi per plateas diſtractus ut proditor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſame year of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>William Wallis</hi> the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief of the Scotiſh Forces, and a Native of that Nation alſo, as the Priſoner was, came into this Kingdom, and being apprehended, was, ſaith <hi>Walfingham fol.</hi> 61. <hi>Londonias uſque ductus &amp; judicialitèr condemnatus, trahitur, ſuſpenditur, &amp; ultimò decollatur,</hi> though he pleaded, as our Hiſtorians tell us, what this Earl doth. That he was a Subject of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and not of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115725:14"/>and therfore ought not to be tried here for Treaſon. In 42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.3. in the Lord <hi>Beaumonts</hi> caſe, when it was replyed that the party, objected againſt to be an Alien, was a Scots man, the plea is no longer inſiſted upon. A protection <hi>quia profecturus</hi> lies not into a Country that is within the allegiance and protection of <hi>England,</hi> 7 <hi>H.</hi> 4.14. yet we ſhall finde the only rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon given, wherefore it was granted into <hi>Scotland,</hi> was, becauſe of the Wars that were then betwixt the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, 7 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.27. After the ceaſing of which Wars, it may be collected by the book, a protection would have lien no more thither, then it would have lien into <hi>Wales</hi> or <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In 13, 14. <hi>Eliz. Dyer.</hi> 304. one was arraigned for a Rape, at the return of the <hi>venire facias</hi> to try him, he pleaded that he was a Scots man, and deſired a <hi>medic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate linguae,</hi> which manner of Tryal is granted to Aliens by the Statutes of 27, &amp; 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. but by the judgment of the Judges of both Benches it was denyed him, for this reaſon amongſt others, becauſe, ſaith the Book, a Scots man was never here reputed for an Alien, but rather a Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Whereas it hath been ſaid, This was becauſe the Statutes of 27, &amp; 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. were made when Scots men were generally reputed Subjects to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, That the Book gives no ſuch reaſon. Secondly, To affirm this, is to ſuppoſe the Iudges, by ſuch a Forreign conceipt, to go againſt the expreſs proviſion of two Acts of Parliament, and the conſtant practiſe in purſuance thereof.</p>
            <p>In the ſame year of 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the caſe of the Duke of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> the evidence of the Biſhop of <hi>Roſs,</hi> a Scots man, was offered againſt the Duke by the Councel for the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115725:14"/>Commonwealth, which the Duke oppoſed from the judgment of <hi>Bracton,</hi> That a Forreigners teſtimony was not in that caſe to be received; but <hi>Cataline</hi> chief Juſtice, though he ſays nothing to <hi>Bractons</hi> opinion touching <hi>exterorum testimonium,</hi> yet he gives the rule of the Court, that the teſtimony was to be received, <hi>Cambdens, Eliz.</hi> 214.</p>
            <p>After this time alſo the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> was tryed in this Kingdom, though not upon the Statute of 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. yet upon the Statute of 27. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 2. then in force; And though in the proceedings of that buſineſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of both Nations met, and that the Scots Commiſſioners did proteſt, that though they did joyn with our Commiſſioners, yet they did thereby make no acknowledgment, that they were other, then a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Nation to this: yet the Engliſh men proteſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Proteſtation, as we finde in the hiſtory of that Queen.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But to paſs from this National to a more Perſonal Conſideration, and from thence (though he were an <hi>Antenatus</hi>) to prove the Earl liable to puniſhment for Treaſon againſt this State, and that by a local allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> wherein it muſt be granted as a principle, and cannot be denyed, but that if an Alien come into this Nation, and there abide, and commit that act which would always be Treaſon in an Engliſh Subject, it is by the Law Treaſon in him during that abode, becauſe he oweth <hi>localem ligeantiam,</hi> and the indictment againſt him ſhall ſay <hi>Contra ligean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae ſuae debitum,</hi> 7. li. <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe. Thus in 36 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. the <hi>Portugals</hi> here in <hi>England</hi> joyn in an Act of Treaſon with Doctor <hi>Loper,</hi> and it was adjudged Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in all. Thus this Earl, though he had been born be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Union, yet he lived in <hi>Scotland</hi> after the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115725:15"/>and at the very time of this Invaſion, whereby he became a Subject, at leaſt <hi>locali ligeanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So in <hi>England</hi> alſo, not onely by his former reſidence here, which he will ſay perhaps was avoyded by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval hence, but by his late coming in, he became <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens</hi> here <hi>locali Ligeantiâ,</hi> becauſe he came from a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom then, by his own confeſſion, in amity with this. This was the caſe of <hi>Sherley</hi> a Frenchman, 4 <hi>Mar.</hi> who came from <hi>France,</hi> then in amity with <hi>England,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken, levying War in an hoſtile manner, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted and executed as a Traytor, <hi>Dyer.</hi> 144. and as the book puts it, 7. <hi>li. Calvins</hi> Caſe, if he had had iſſue here that iſſue ſhould have inherited.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In the next place, I ſhall prove the Earl of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> (though he had been an <hi>antenatus</hi>) to be a Subject of England <hi>Ligeantiâ acquiſitâ,</hi> and that by the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization of his Father or by his own denization, but firſt as to the naturalization of his Father.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Act of Parliament hath been read and proved whereby the Father of this Earl by the name of <hi>James</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in 21 <hi>Jac.</hi> was naturalized to be to all intents and purpoſes a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ect of this Nation, as if he had been here born, with a further clauſe, that his heirs might inherit and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe any Lands, Tenements, &amp;c. By which Act it clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear that this Earl is naturalized alſo. For, 1. Though in the caſe of a denization, there may need the word Heir, to extend it to them, becauſe it goes as it is limited, it may be for life, in tayl, or upon condition, 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.7. yet its repugnant to ſuppoſe, that, in point of a naturalization, becauſe he that is born in <hi>England,</hi> as by relation this makes him, without any other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, conveys the right to his heirs: Hence Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization is never <hi>temporanea</hi> though <hi>data</hi> 1. <hi>Jnſt.</hi> 129.2.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115725:15"/>Here are not wanting words neither that reach to the heirs, if neceſſary; for the Act is, That his Heirs may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit and purchaſe, &amp;c. And in purſuance hereof its no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that this Earl hath done both; But we ſhall finde, that oftentimes no more goes to expreſs a Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lization then this: No other expreſſion is uſed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the priviledg of being Engliſh to them that are born of Engliſh Parents beyond Sea, but onely that they may have and freely bear the inheritance within the ſame allegiance as other inheritors, 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>de natis ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Mare.</hi> And in 3 <hi>H.</hi> 6.55. <hi>Hall</hi> and his wiſe brought a Writ of <hi>Dover,</hi> the Tenant pleaded that the Feme was an alien, the Demandants reply, that the Feme in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 4. was inabled by Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament to purchaſe Lands &amp; Tenements, &amp;c. with which Reply the Defendants Counſel reſted ſatisfied, as if the Replication expreſſed it ſufficiently that ſhe was natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralized, and thereupon demanded view.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it hath been objected, That this Act can have no other effect, then if the now Earls Father had been born in <hi>England;</hi> and though he were a Native Engliſh-man, yet having iſſue, this Earl, by a Native Scotſ-woman in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the iſſue thereby remains an Alien though his Father were Naturalized or born in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſhall eaſily grant, both that this Earl was ſo born in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that the Naturalization amounts to no more then if the old Earl had been born in <hi>England,</hi> but do deny the inference drawn from thence, That ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the now Earl muſt be an Alien. For though in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times ſome Controverſie hath been touching this queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the iſſue of an Engliſh man, going out of the Kingdom, born of an alien woman, ſhall be a Subject of <hi>England,</hi> or no? Yet I take the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115725:16"/>Law to be clear at this day, that ſuch iſſue is a Subject of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the common Law, if Father and Mother, both Engliſh, have iſſue beyond ſea, that iſſue is Engliſh, 1 <hi>R.</hi> 3.4. the Statute of 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>de natis ultra mare,</hi> being declarative of the common Law, 42 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. and if the reaſon and practice of the Law be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned we ſhall finde it to be the ſame, where the father only is Engliſh, for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe at this day any perſon may go from this Kingdom to another without licenſe, though he be neither Nobleman, Merchant, or Soldier, except ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint by a <hi>ne exeat regnum,</hi> Proclamation, or other Act of State be againſt him, ſo is it reſolved, 12, 13 <hi>Eliz. Dyer.</hi> 296. And though all, except perſons ſo qualified, were reſtrained by 5 <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. yet that Statute is repealed by the Statute of 4 <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 1. made principally in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Scotland;</hi> Therefore however the Law may be as to ſuch as go when prohibited, or who ſtay beyond Sea when commanded to return; yet as to all others at this day, and always as to Noblemen, as the father of this Earl was, upon whom no reſtraint was ever put by Common or Statute Law, certainly the Law is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, eſpecially when the removal is to a Country in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, as <hi>Scotland</hi> was.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Partus ſequitur ſemen</hi> by the Common Law, therefore in 4 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Statham villenage</hi> 9. if a free man marry a wife, and have iſſue, that iſſue is free; but otherwiſe, if the man had been villain and the woman free.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The woman alien by the marriage is indeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and the iſſue then muſt needs partake of the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and it appears by 26 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>rot. Parl.</hi> 1. that when <hi>Edmond,</hi> the brother of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. who marryed the Queen
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115725:16"/>of <hi>Navar,</hi> dyed, all the Judges reſolved, ſhe ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and what though ſhe ſhould not, as in other caſes it hath been doubted; Yet that hinders not, but during co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture ſhe was endenized, and thats enough to endenize the iſſue. If a wife marry a free man, it is and hath been a doubt, whether this be a perpetual infranchiſement to the woman after the death of her Baron, but it never was doubted, but that both her ſelf, during coverture, and her iſſue ever after were infranchiſed, <hi>Lit. ſect.</hi> 187. 1 <hi>Inſtit.</hi> 136.</p>
            <p>And for expreſs authority in the point in hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ancient authority of, <hi>Abridg. Aſſ.</hi> 39. <hi>tit. Baſtard.</hi> 7. and <hi>Bro. Denizen</hi> 21. it was the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Judges of <hi>England,</hi> 2 <hi>Ca.</hi> in the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy Chamber, betwixt the King and <hi>Eaton,</hi> uſually called <hi>Stephenſons</hi> Caſe, the Record whereof is ready to be produced, where Judg <hi>Yelverton</hi> and <hi>Harvey,</hi> then Judges Aſſiſtants to that Court, declared it to be their judgments, as alſo of all the other Judges, That the two Sons of <hi>Stephenſon,</hi> born beyond Sea upon the body of an Alien, were Denizens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> I obſerved but one book cited for maintenance of the contrary opinion, and that was 26 <hi>H.</hi> 6. where indeed it is 22 <hi>H.</hi> 6.38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Which Authority is againſt, not for that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for which it is cited; for in an Action there brought, the Defendant pleads, that the Plaintiffs an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtor, in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 4. went beyond Sea without Licence, and there bad iſſue the Plaintiff: upon this plea, <hi>Arderne</hi> the Plaintiffs Councel demurs; but ſaith the book, <hi>Priſot</hi> the Defendants Councel durſt not demur.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If the book were as it is ſuppoſed, yet it makes nothing againſt the Law at this day, becauſe by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115725:17"/>the Book it appears, that the Plaintiffs anceſtor went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 4. without licence, which being after <hi>R.</hi> 2. there was a reſtraint upon him, except by licence, or qualified as that Statute of <hi>R.</hi> 2. requires, which Reſtraint is now abrogated as is before ſaid; and the Inhabitants of <hi>England,</hi> as is ſuitable to all Iſlanders, may travel at pleaſure, except eſpecially forbidden; and ſo whatever the Law was then, its otherwiſe now, <hi>mutataratione legis mutatur lex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> What if the preſent Earl did himſelf endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, or, as he ſaith, was adviſed, notwithſtanding the Naturalization of of his Father, to procure himſelf to be Naturalized, or indenized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yet that could be but <hi>in majorem caut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lam;</hi> as ſome ſavings have been inſerted into Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment themſelves, not for neceſſity, but for ſatisfaction of the Lay Gent. as our books expreſs it, 1. <hi>li. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 24. <hi>Plow. Com.</hi> 379. upon the Statute of 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. and even in that caſe of <hi>Stephenſon,</hi> though the Iudges aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants delivered what was their own opinions and of the reſt of the Iudges, yet if making the party a Denizen would end the controverſie, they did adviſe it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Beſides this purchaſe of his Fathers, the Earl hath himſelf contributed to his own Denization, not ſo much by inheriting his Fathers dignity, and purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and enjoying himſelf Lands in <hi>England,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rather an evidence of what he formerly was, then making him what he was not before; but by the Writ of ſummons ſent to this Earl himſelf, 15 <hi>Car.</hi> The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord whereof hath been read, commanding him <hi>ex fide &amp; ligeantia ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to appear in Parliament as a Peer of this Realm, who accordingly did appear, and acted in this Parliament, being choſen of ſeveral Committees in the Lords Houſe, to conſider of many things of great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115725:17"/>concernment, ſome whereof were for the ſtrength of the Nation, as hath been fully proved by the Records of the Lords Houſe; all which actions are ſo inconſiſtent with his being an alien, and would be ſuch a ſoleciſm in State to admit an alien to be inveſted amongſt others with a judicial power, that rather then it ſhould be admitted, all this layd together will (I conceive) amount to, at leaſt, a Denization.</p>
            <p>I will not ſay that the granting of every office, or the being employed in any tranſaction, which concerns the Law or Government of the Kingdom, will make an Alien a Denizen; the books of 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.1. and 14 <hi>H.</hi> 4.19. forbid me to ſay ſo, but it's another thing to have a judicial power in Parliament, and to ſit by virtue of ſuch ſummons in the Parliament of <hi>England:</hi> The Lord <hi>De-la Ware</hi> was diſabled to ſit in the Houſe of Peers du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his life; but he dying, and a Writ of Summons coming to his Son, he was by vertue thereof enabled, not onely to ſit, but to enjoy that place which his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors formerly had done, 11 <hi>li. Coo.</hi> 1. and in 39. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Umfravil</hi> Earl of <hi>Angos</hi> ought to be named Earl in the Writ againſt him, becauſe by that name he was ſummoned to the Parliament, and for not naming him ſo, the Writ abated; A Denization is a kinde of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Manumiſſion: Now as there is in Law an expreſs infranchiſement of a Villain, and an infranchiſement in Law, <hi>Lit. ſect.</hi> 205. So it may be ſaid of Denizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And amongſt other Manumiſſions by Act in Law, I finde in <hi>Britton, fol.</hi> 79. &amp; 82. if a Villain were made a Knight, this did make him free <hi>rations dignitatis,</hi> and did not make the conferring of that dignity to be a voyd act, paralel whereunto is the caſe in hand.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The laſt thing I ſhall inſiſt upon, touching this ſecond part of the plea, is to make it appear, that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115725:18"/>though the Earl had been born before the Union, and an Alien, that yet there are other circumſtances in this caſe yet remaining, which will clearly make this Act of his to amount to no leſs then Treaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> His coming from a Kingdom in amity with this, and his marching in hither with Engliſh Traytors; That he marcht in and held correſpondency with Sir <hi>Marma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke Langdale</hi> and his ſon, and with Sir <hi>Thomas Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and divers others, hath been fully proved; And that that Kingdom was then in amity with this, beſides the National Treaties and Engagements unrepealed, it appears as well by the Earls own confeſſions at the Bar, as by the words of the Scotiſh Declaration made upon this expedition, read at the Earls own requeſt, which, what ever it be, doth yet conclude this Earl and all his party from alledging the contrary for their advantage, it having been often reiterated by him; and alſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſaid, That this expedition was neither againſt the Parliament nor People of <hi>England;</hi> beſides, that it is no ſleight matter to make Nations in amity to become open Enemies in a legal conſtruction, which we are now upon, as appears by the book of 19 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>Now that theſe Circumſtances will make this Act reach to Treaſon, appears by theſe Authorities of Law. In the days of Queen <hi>Mary, France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> were in amity, <hi>Sherley,</hi> a French Native, during that amity, joyns himſelf with ſome Engliſh Traytors, <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> is apprehended and indicted as a Traytor <hi>contra lige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antiae ſuae debitum,</hi> 4 <hi>Mar. Dyer.</hi> 144. which is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for good Law likewiſe, 7 <hi>li.</hi> in <hi>Calvins</hi> Caſe by all the Judges, with which agrees <hi>Brook. Treaſon.</hi> 32. and <hi>Crompton</hi> Juriſdiction of Courts 72. and Mr Juſtice <hi>Dalliſons</hi> Reports 3, 4. <hi>Mar.</hi> All which Authorities agree in this difference, That if Alien Enemies joyn
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115725:18"/>with Engliſh Rebels, and be apprehended, the Aliens ſhall be tryed by Martial Law, or ranſom'd; but if Alien amies ſo joyn, its Treaſon in all; and 'tis obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that the caſe is put cautelouſly, in <hi>H.</hi> 4. and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg'd by <hi>Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Treaſon.</hi> 1. That where Alien Enemies joyn with Engliſh, the Aliens ſhall be tryed by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Law, and the Engliſh as Traytors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> The Objection hath been made, and ſo far it ſeems the Law is agreed, That if Aliens fight under the banner of Engliſh, that this may be Treaſon in all, but not if the Engliſh fight under the command of Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, which is alledged to be the caſe in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, I cannot ſafely admit that which the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection takes for granted, that the Engliſh were the Auxiliaries, and the Scots the principals in this act, when I finde it in the proof offered by the Earl himſelf, that he came in by the invitation of their friends in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and when I remember what was deſigned and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in the South of <hi>England</hi> before and at the ſame time with this expedition. 2. But admit it to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, yet if this difference were material, then it ſhould follow likewiſe, That if Alien enemies did fight under an Engliſh Command, it ſhould be Treaſon in all, but it is not ſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Law makes no ſuch difference, nay the very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection ſeems to be made and anſwered, 4. <hi>Mar. Dyer.</hi> 144. for the book ſaith, that though <hi>Sherley</hi> were an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien, yet <hi>hoc non refort tempore pacis inter Anglos et Galles,</hi> the weight is layd upon <hi>tempus pacic</hi> onely.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The true reaſon of the Law in one caſe is the ſame in both, which I conceive to be from the deteſtation of conſpiring with an inward ſecret enemy, and from the truſt the Law repoſeth in ſuch as are of a Country in amity. There is no Treaſon, but where there is a Truſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115725:19"/>hence anciently Treaſon, in its genuine and original ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, was onely and properly amongſt allyes and friends, who mutually did repoſe confidence in each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as may be ſeen in the Mirror, <hi>f.</hi> 30. and 201. And that a greater truſt was placed in Aliens amies, then in others, appears in that our Law allows not onely Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique and Commerce with them, but alſo allows them to be to ſome purpoſes Denizens, namely as to the bringing perſonal actions, which if they bring, it ſhall not be allowed to plead that the Plaintiffs are Aliens, 19 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4, 6. &amp; 6 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Dy.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But the Earl hath objected, that upon the Scotiſh Forces coming in under his Command, they of that Nation were by the Houſe of Commons voted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and thoſe of this Kingdom, who adhered to them, Traytors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The words of that Vote ſeem to be excluſive of the Priſoner, mentioning only thoſe under his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. 2. Though every enemy in the legal ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word, be not a Traytor, yet every Traytor is an enemy, and therefore if now he be proved a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, he may be well enough an Enemy within that Vote; The preſent Charge againſt him is a Charge of High Treaſon, yet the concluſion doth not improperly pray Judgment againſt him both as a Traytor and publique Enemy. 3. Take the words in the ſtricteſt ſence, and the Vore onely names thoſe of the Scotiſh Nation Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but thoſe of this Kingdom Traytors; Now the labor hath been, and I ſuppoſe it clear that the Earl himſelf is of this Nation, and ſo a Traytor by that Vote from which he would derive an Argument for himſelf. 4. If yet any other conſtruction ſhould be made, <hi>Leges poſteriores priores abrogant,</hi> he is, by the Act whereby this Court now ſits, ordered to be tryed for Treaſon in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115725:19"/>the ſame kinde as the reſt, who are now under queſtion; and if his fact be Treaſon, it will eaſily follow by an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of <hi>a denominatis,</hi> that he is a Traytor.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third part of the Earl of <hi>Cambridg</hi> his Plea is, That he is a priſoner of War, and rendred upon Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and that thoſe capitulations were made before his Rendition with Major General <hi>Lamberts</hi> Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners.</p>
            <p>That there were Articles, and he a priſoner of War, I ſhall agree to be prov'd, as alſo that one of thoſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles was, That he ſhould have quarter, and have his life aſſured, and it muſt be agreed on the other hand, That the Lord <hi>Gray,</hi> who had equal authority, proteſted from the firſt againſt that Treaty, and after took him priſoner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any aſſent thereunto: But whether, by the proof, the Earl were not a priſoner before the ſigning the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and whether before the Articles were to have any effect, the ſame were not to be ratified by the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in chief, is ſubmitted to judgment upon the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. That therefore I may do the priſoner right in this point, which he ſeems to make his ſtrongeſt <hi>aſylum,</hi> I ſhall admit that there were ſuch Articles, and wave the relying upon the other Circumſtances, which may not ſeem ſo clear in proof.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs I ſhall briefly ſhew my Reaſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I apprehend no ſecurity from the ſtroke of civil Juſtice, belongs to the priſoner by this Refuge; for as to the military is not the contention.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If theſe Articles be of avayl, againſt the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power of the State, they muſt in effect amount to a pardon or diſcharge of Treaſon, (for this point doth take the laſt point by admittance, <hi>viz.</hi> that the fact is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.) Now though the military Power may exempt a priſoner of War from the execution of the Sword, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115725:20"/>of their own Power, yet it is not in their power, nor do they aſſume, or ever challenged ſuch a power, as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt Delinquents and Traytors from the execution of the Magiſtrate, for the bringing of whom to condign puniſhment the Souldier was at firſt armed, and the war principally begun; and if it ſhould be in the power of one Soldier, it would <hi>pari ratione</hi> be in the power of all, as wel to ſpare all as one; and if to grant a pardon of life, then likewiſe for their livelyhoods; and ſo the end of the War, and the ſatisfaction promiſed, would be in the power of the ſervants of the State to fruſtrate; not that the Articles have no effect, for he was by them freed from the immediate execution of the Sword.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The pardoning of Treaſon is a power ſo inſeparable to the ſupream Power, that by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of Law it is not communicable to any other, in 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.123. its made a great doubt, and ſo ſaid to be 1 <hi>Bro: Treaſon.</hi> 22. Mercy and Juſtice being not transferable, 7. <hi>li. Co.</hi> in the caſe of Penall Statutes. 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.2. and 20 <hi>H.</hi> 7.6. It's true indeed, there was a time when ſome had gotten this power into their hands, but by the Statute of 27 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. this power was reſumed into the ſupream Power, and there it hath ſince lodg'd; and however we diſpute not what the Parliament may do by expreſs words, as they have done in many Acts and Tenders of Indemnity, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch expreſſions, not by any implicite power, nor <hi>ex officio,</hi> can any juſtly aſſume it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, By the Rules of Law no Officer or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of State can give away or diſpence with the Intereſt of the Common wealth; if a Cuſtomer, who is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of State, take a Bond in his own name for the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Bulloigne, he cannot diſcharge this Bond. 4 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.4. and 12. The King was the ſupream Officer
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115725:20"/>of the Common-wealth, yet if an Indictment of Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance had been preferred againſt one in his name, it had not been in his power to have diſcharged this offence, 3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Fitz. Aſſ.</hi> 445. nor could he for the ſame Reaſon by any <hi>non obſtante</hi> diſpence with the penalty of any Statute which did concern the Intereſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, 12 <hi>Jac:</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Ingrams</hi> Caſe, and <hi>H.</hi> 36. <hi>Eli:</hi> betwixt <hi>Hamond</hi> and <hi>Griffith,</hi> in an Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation upon a penal Statute, the Informer dyed, yet the Kings Attorney might proceed. The difference I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend to be, as to the point in hand, betwixt one try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by Martial Law meerly, as an Alien enemy is, for ſuch a one being tryable by the Sword, if taken, may be diſcharged by that power, though in that Caſe I totally exclude not the legiſlative Power; but for a Traytor ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally and legally, only tryable by the municipal Laws of a State, to be abſolutely diſcharged by a ſubordinate power, without the Concurrence or Confirmation of the Magiſtrate, will ever be ſtrange to me, till I find that Rule overthrown of <hi>nil dat quod babe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which can never be in a juſt and moral ſence.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, However the words ſound, the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and true meaning of the parties was not to free thoſe that were concerned from Juſtice, if the State required it; and intentions are the beſt Rules for conſtruction in theſe caſes: That it was intended only in this Treaty to free the priſoner from the preſent execution of the Sword by Martial Law, and no otherwiſe, hath been ſworn by two of thoſe Gentlemen that were Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners under Major General <hi>Lambert;</hi> who have ſworn their own intentions: Words, ſaith <hi>Bracton,</hi> are but <hi>veſtiment a rerum,</hi> as the body and outward form; the true meaning and intention of parties is the life and ſoul of every contract: as for <hi>ſenſus leteralis</hi> it hath been (I have
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115725:21"/>obſerved) <hi>via regia,</hi> but it hath not proved unto that ſide <hi>via tuta:</hi> However words found, the expoſition muſt be <hi>ſecundum ſubjectam materiam.</hi> In 41 <hi>E.</hi> 3.6. if one having divers faculties hath an annuity granted to him <hi>pro concilio impenſo,</hi> the words are general, but it ſhall be conſtrued for counſel in that art which was intended: And as <hi>Brudnel</hi> ſaith, in 14 <hi>H.</hi> 8.2. Contracts ſhall be expounded according to the intents of thoſe that did contract. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, ſpeaking <hi>de juſtitia,</hi> as a Judg, not as an Advocate, <hi>fol.</hi> 24. to cavil with words againſt the mind of the parties <hi>eſt calumnia quaedam &amp; malitioſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> interpretatio;</hi> in which place he puts a Caſe upon a Treaty, as ours is, of one who had made a truce for one hundred and thirty days with his enemy, and taking ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Letter, fell upon his enemy in the night, alledging the truce was only for days, which the Orator derides as meer injuſtice, and no otherwiſe may the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral conſtruction, contended for, be in the preſent Caſe, except the letter muſt be obſerved, or not obſerved, as it proves advantageous or diſadvantageous to the priſoner; beſides its uſual in Law, That by averments the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of parties take place where the letter would not ſo decide the queſtion, as 5 <hi>li. Coo.</hi> 68. and 21 <hi>R.</hi> 2: <hi>Fitz. deviſ.</hi> 27. Nor do I ſee, how in the pening thoſe Articles, any other expreſſions could well have been; if proviſion had been made, that the priſoner ſhould have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the power of civil Juſtice, that had been voyd; and if it had been expreſſed, that nothing was by thoſe Articles intended to exempt him from civil Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that had alſo implyed a power in them, if they had ſeen cauſe to have given an abſolute diſcharge from the Magiſtrate, which had been equally by conſtruction de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory to the civil Power.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If the Earl had ever been <hi>de facto</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:115725:21"/>yet he may ſeem to have loſt the benefit therof by his eſcape made after a ſpecial promiſe to the Governor with whom he was priſoner; the Civil Law, as <hi>Forteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue</hi> obſerves, <hi>cap.</hi> 46. <hi>Libertinum ingratum in pristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam redigit ſervitutem,</hi> and our Law ſaith, if one hath committed a capital Crime, and, being pardoned after, do but break the peace, he forfeits the benefit of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. 3 <hi>H.</hi> 7.7. As <hi>Bartue</hi> did the benefit of his Licenſe to travel, by his reſort to the Fugitives, 2 <hi>Eli. Dy.</hi> 176. And I conceive no difference, whether the condition be expreſſed or implyed, which I infer not to make the eſcape Treaſon, being not ſo charged, and the Statutes of 2 <hi>H.</hi> 6. and 14 <hi>Eliz.</hi> being expired concerning that, but only for this purpoſe it is enforced, that he who ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf up a priſoner of War, and had for that conſideration quarter granted him, and yet after breaks that which was on his part to be performed, hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deprived himſelf of that priviledg which otherwiſe he might have enjoyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If now the Priſoner ſhall be queſtioned for his life, who by the rendition of himſelf had quarter given him for it, how is the Conſideration made good which did induce him to ſurrender; beſides, there if he had dyed (as the Earl himſelf ſaid) he had preſerved his eſtate, and avoyded the conſequences of Attainder?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It's ſtrange that it ſhould be thought no privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg to have ſo much time to dye, in caſe there were cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of it, above a death by a military execution, which uſually is ſudden and <hi>ſine ſtrepitu Judicii.</hi> 2. Is it no priviledg above an immediate death by the Sword, to have a fair judicial proceeding by a Charge againſt him, putting in his own plea thereunto, the matter of fact by witneſſes and other evidence proved on both ſides, and Counſel aſſigned him of his own choyce to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115725:22"/>his Cauſe in point of Law, and himſelf to be heard as much as he could ſpeak in his own Defence? 3. And the danger ſeems by this manner of Tryal not greater then before, for he that dyes a Traytor <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> becauſe himſelf is the cauſe why formalities of legal proceedings againſt him cannot be obſerved, by the ancient Law forfeited his eſtate, and remained attainted notwithſtanding, <hi>Plowd. Com.</hi> 262. <hi>Fitz. Dower.</hi> 106. where, in a Writ of <hi>Dower,</hi> the Demandant was bart'd for that her husband went into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and joyning himſelf with the enemies, dyed in emnity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> As to the examples of <hi>Joſuah</hi> with the <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> and of the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> forbidding the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſmite thoſe whom he had taken captive with his Sword and Bow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I anſwer, As to the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Joſhua</hi> with the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> God forbid but that as that, ſo all other Leagues and Treaties ſhould be kept ſo far as to bind that power that made them, and who can rationally expect more? Now <hi>Joſuah</hi> was the Succeſſor of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and a Magiſtrate as well as Commander; Beſides, the ſaid the Princes of the Congregation ſwore unto them, and had theſe Circumſtances been incident to this Caſe, the diſpute had been ended.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the other inſtance, the men of <hi>Syria</hi> had a perſonal quarrel againſt <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and therefore none being intereſted but the Prophet, it might well become his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety to be their Interceſſor. 2. For any thing appears. the Prophet only ſpeaks againſt their being ſmitten with the Sword of War, which, if it had been drawn in cold blood, might have been the blood of War in Peace but not againſt the Sword of Civil Juſtice. 3. Theſe enemies were taken in the midſt of <hi>Samaria intr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> praeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and therefore bread and water might well be ſet
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115725:22"/>before them, that they might eat and go to their maſters; but there hath been in this caſe much blood drawn, and miſchief done; for the avenging and ſatisfaction where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Juſtice cries to them that bear not the Sword in vain.</p>
            <p>And now (my Lord) though I might have demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Judgment for want of the Priſoners making good his own plea, which he ought to have done before I had ſaid any thing to the contrary; the plea of being an Alien lying on his part to prove that pleads it, 9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.12. and <hi>Dy.</hi> 300. And the plea of a Pardon, being a confeſsion of the Fact, if not made out, proves fatal and final alſo to the party, <hi>Stanf: cor.</hi> 150. Yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, for that the Priſoner hath not been confined herein to the ſtrict formalities of the Law, I have alſo, on the behalf of the Commonwealth, taken the priviledg of ſpeaking thus much for aſſerting the invalidity of his Plea. And therefore, upon the whole matter, having now ſaid what hath prevailed with my judgment to offer in this caſe, I humbly ſubmit the ſame to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Conſideration of this Honorable Court.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Correct with thy pen theſe following ſlips.</head>
            <p>Page 11. line 10. for <hi>endeavor</hi> read <hi>endeavoring.</hi> P. 14. l. 22. for <hi>que r. qui.</hi> P. 16. l. 19. for <hi>Garden</hi> r. <hi>Gardian.</hi> P. 22. l. 1. for <hi>ſav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> r. <hi>ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> l. 28. for <hi>we truſt</hi> r. <hi>no truſt.</hi> P. 27. l. 31. blot out the figure 2. l. 32. for <hi>Loper</hi> r. <hi>Lopez.</hi> P. 28. l. 6. for <hi>Ligens</hi> r. <hi>Ligeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Whare <hi>Dover</hi> is r. <hi>Dower,</hi> P. 32. l. 17. for <hi>Lay Gent.</hi> 1. <hi>Lay Gents.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
